Guide to the Naval History Society Collection 1721-1995 (bulk 1781-1936) MS 439
New-York Historical Society
- Series 27. Isaac Hull (1798-1841)
  1833: Commands USS Constitution after its reconstruction
  1838: Appointed Commodore of Mediterranean Squadron
  1839-1841: Commands European Squadron flagship USS Ohio
  1841: Retires from active duty
  1843: Dies 13 February in Philadelphia
  - Log Book, US Frigate Constitution, 1798 December 6 - 1800 October 20 (Volume 1)
  - Letter book, 1809 October 28 - 1811 March 16 (Volume 2)
  - Remark Book and Journal, US Frigate Constitution, 1810 June 17 - 1811 July 19 (Volume 3)
  - Letter book, 1811 March 29 - November 27 (Volume 4)
  - Log, US Frigate Constitution, 1811 August 2 - 1812 August 19 (Volume 5)
  - Letter book, 1813 February 25 - 1814 March 13 (Volume 6)
  - Letter book, 1814 March 16 - [1815] March 17 (Volume 7)
  - Letter book, 1823 October 25, - 1827 July 2 (Volume 8)
  - Letter book, USS United States, 1823 October 25 -1827 November 7 (Volume 9)
  - Order Book, 1823 November 24 - 1827 April 29 (Volume 10)
  - Letter book and orders received, 1824 August 10 - 1840 October 12 (Volume 11)
  - Letter book, 1829 May 14 - 1831 June 25 (Volume 12)
  - Letter book, 1829 September 18 - 1835 October 18 (Volume 13)
  - Letters to Secretary of Navy, USS Ohio, 1838 August 27-1840 February 12 (Volume 14)
  - Orders and correspondence, USS Ohio, 1838 Sept 20 - 1840 August 2 (Volume 15)
  - Letter book, USS Ohio, 1838 September 20 - 1841 July 2 (Volume 16)
  - Journal and letter book, 1838 October- 1841 August 2 (Volume 17)
  - Letters to Navy Commissioners, USS Ohio, 1840 February -1841 September 13 (Volume 18)
- Series 28. John Paul Jones (1776-1976; bulk 1907-1930)
  The series includes five 18th century documents from the collection of John Sanford Barnes (Series 3) related to the exploits of John Paul Jones; and supporting material about Jones either produced or collected by both Barnes and his son Col. James Barnes (Series 4). The series documents Jones himself, the history of the Barnes's collecting of Jones-related information and objects, and their efforts to determine the authenticity and veracity of these. It includes John Sanford Barnes's correspondence with various Jones biographers and collectors, typed transcripts of Jones's ships' logbooks and personal correspondence, photoreproductions of original items in Barnes's and other collections, clippings and other published materials, Col. James Barnes's writings on Jones, and undated and unattributed notes about the provenance and acquisition of Jones-related material.
  The original documents carry the signatures of Jones himself on a letter to DeNeufville introducing John Barry and, on his commission aboard Providence, that of John Hancock. The clippings document a report of the finding of Jones's body in Paris in 1903, the 1909 appearance of Ranger's logbooks and a separate auction of Jones material, information from the Russian archives in 1926, and the Naval History Society's participation in placement of a new headstone at the grave of Jones's brother William Jones in Fredericksburg, VA, in 1930. It is not clear who added the 1976 clipping on the purported finding of the wreck of Bon Homme Richard.
  The correspondence documents organizations and individuals interested in Jones material, including the Library of Congress (the Manuscripts Division published "A calendar of John Paul Jones manuscripts in the Library of Congress" in 1903); biographer Anna deKoven (author of the 1913 "The letters of John Paul Jones"); and Grenville Kane, the Naval History Society's treasurer who was acknowledged as the greatest collector of Jones material. There is both a clean and an edited version of the typed transcript of Jones's correspondence, which Col. James Barnes may have planned to publish.
  Some of the photocopied material shows penciled notes on the original items' provenance and history. The Beaumont Groube material documents John Sanford Barnes's effort to determine, through a handwriting comparison, the writer of Serapis's logbook (see Series 49). Photocopies of Jones's sealing wax imprint on the DeNeufville letter fueled continuing speculation about whether the seal itself had originally been a gift to him from Marie Antoinette.
  The commission signed by Hancock, Jones's letter to DeNeufville, and correspondence to and from Barnes about Jones are available on microfilm.
  John Paul Jones is among the most romantic and written-about figures in Revolutionary history. His raising of the first American flag aboard a naval vessel in 1776, his response to the British call to surrender Bon Homme Richard of "I have not yet begun to fight," and his victory aboard that vessel over Serapis in 1779 are elements of American nation-building with almost mythic significance. John Sanford Barnes's Jones collection was a product of his general interest in naval history (with a focus on heroic exploits) magnified by his often-mentioned family connection with Jones's contemporaries Commodore Bainbridge (see Series 1) and Admiral Barry (see Series 5): Barnes's wife's grandfather James Hayes was a nephew of and adopted by John Barry; his wife's mother was Bainbridge's daughter, Sarah Bainbridge Hayes.
  The early 20th century saw the publication of many biographies and articles about Jones's personal life and exploits. Their prevalence is perhaps attributable to the general increased focus on naval contributions to military victories after the Spanish American War in 1898 and efforts to build a "new American navy" for the new century. In 1900 August Buell published the widely quoted and later disparaged "Paul Jones: Founder of the American Navy"; in 1905 James Barnes's own "The personal appearance of John Paul Jones" was published in Appleton's Booklover's Magazine. The Naval History Society's first publication was "Logs of the Serapis, Alliance, and Ariel under the Command of John Paul Jones, 1778-1780," edited by John Sanford Barnes, and printed by De Vinne Press, New York, in 1911, based on the original and transcribed logbooks (see Series 49) in his personal collection. Anna deKoven's biography (for which she consulted Barnes and his collection) was published in 1913, and in 1917 Don Seitz published "Paul Jones: His exploits in English seas during 1778 to 1780." Each added new information and raised further questions about details of Jones's life and genealogy, accomplishments, death, and burial, which were discussed both privately in correspondence among authors and collectors, and publicly in newspaper letters columns.
  The 18th century materials are arranged chronologically. The thematic organization of Barnes's collection-related material in its original housing has been retained and those folders are arranged chronologically. The undated material is ordered with original writings first, followed by transcripts and photoreproduced images.
  Additional correspondence received by John Sanford Barnes about John Paul Jones can be found in the Naval History Society's Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection (see Series 52).
  Series 49 (Logbooks: US Navy) of the Naval History Society Collection includes transcripts of the logbooks of Ranger and Bon Homme Richard and the original one-volume logbooks of Serapis, Alliance, and Ariel.
  Barnes described the history of his collecting of Jones-related and other naval memorabilia in his 1902 lecture "Naval Literature" to the U.S. Naval Institute, published in Proceedings of the United States Naval Institute, vol XXIX, no. 2, whole no. 106 (XN E182 .B26).
  - Jones letter to Admiral E. Hopkins, 1776 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commission to command sloop Providence, 1776 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - DeMartine letter on outfitting Bon Homme Richard, 1779 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jones letter introducing John Barry, 1783 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Browne letter, 1789 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to J.S. Barnes about Jones, 1905, 1909, 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed material: general, 1906-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings and correspondence: Jones's appearance and portraiture, 1907-1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: General, 1909-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Material on logbooks: Correspondence, photoreproduction, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Material on Bon Homme Richard's flag: Clipping, photograph, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Visual materials: Photographs, postcard, commemorative stamps, 1931, 1936, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Material on Jones's naval commission: Correspondence, clippings, photoreproduction, 1931, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Material on Hancock-signed commission, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Miscellaneous writings by Col. James Barnes about John Paul Jones", Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Transcripts of Jones's letters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Typescript: Letters of John Paul Jones, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Corrected typescript: Letters of John Paul Jones, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Typescript: "An Alphabetical List of Letters to Sundry Persons Contained in the Book", Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photoreproductions of Jones documents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photoreproduction, Beaumont Groube letter; J.S. Barnes note, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photoreproductions of Jones's letter introducing Barry, and Barry's seal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - DeKoven article on Jones; correspondence with J.S. Barnes, 1906-1910 (Box OS 1, Folder 13)
  - Transcripts and photostats of Jones's letter to Admiral Hopkins, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 14)
- Series 29. Edward Yorke McCauley (1845-1877)
  The series consists of McCauley's illustrated seamanship and gunnery notebook, kept while he was a midshipman at Annapolis and including notes on astronomy, signals, and maneuvers; his illustrated and highly detailed diary kept aboard USS Powhatan during its visit to Japan under Commodore Matthew Perry; orders and telegrams received; as well as letterpress copies of official correspondence sent, most while McCauley commanded USS Lackawanna as part of the Asiatic Squadron. The correspondence discusses personnel issues, local problems likely to affect American interests, and relations with Europeans and Americans in ports including Nagasaki and Yokohama, Japan; Shanghai, China; and Hong Kong.
  The correspondence received had been disbound from a scrapbook and numbered chronologically in red china marker, probably preparatory to microfilming.
  The correspondence and the letterpress book (Volume 3) are available on microfilm.
  The 1854 diary was edited by Allan Cole and published in 1942 by Princeton University Press as "With Perry in Japan: The diary of Edward Y. McCauley" (DS809.U5 M2).
  Edward Yorke McCauley (1827-1894), born in Tripoli while his father served there as US Consul, had an illustrious naval career: serving on various vessels on the African coast in the 1850s, as part of the coastal blockade during the Civil War, and rising through the ranks of commander (1866), fleet captain and chief of staff of the North Atlantic Squadron (1867), captain (1872) while serving in the Pacific, commodore (1881), and rear admiral (1885). In 1881 he was elected fellow of the American Philosophical Society, and was the author of works on Egyptology including a dictionary of hieroglyphics published by the Society.
  As a midshipman in 1852 he was aboard USS Powhatan, the flagship of Admiral Matthew Perry, when it departed Norfolk for Japan and entered Tokyo Bay on February 14, 1854. Perry oversaw signing of the first treaty with Japan on March 31, opening that country to commercial contact with the West.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital copy of the diary is available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Correspondence received, 1872 November 20 - 1873 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence received, 1873 June 28 - November 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence received, 1873 November 22 -1874 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence received, 1874 March 16 - September 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence received, 1874 Sept 29 - November 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Orders and telegrams, 1874 October 28 - 1876 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photoreproductions, color: Japan diary, 1854, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photoreproductions, black and white: Japan diary, 1854, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Seamanship and gunnery, 1845 January 9 - 1847 April 14 (Volume 1)
  - Diary, 1853 February 13 - 1854 June 10 (Volume 2)
  - Letterpress book, 1873 August - 1877 March (Volume 3)
- Series 30. Richard Worsam Meade, 2nd (1836-1865, 1871, 1976)
  The collection is comprised of materials related to the crew of brig Washington and prize claims for capture of Amistad; correspondence and records from Meade's command of various vessels and at the New York Navy Yard; detailed information about San Jacinto under his command, including the salvage of its equipment after it was wrecked; materials related to the inquiry into John McLaughlin's conduct during the Florida campaign against the Seminole Indians; Meade's efforts to make Spanish translations of notable American documents available after the Mexican-American War; a statement from his estate; and a newspaper clipping about the reconstructed Amistad's participation in Operation Sail.
  One of the lists of officers aboard Washington during its capture of Amistad and the prize money apportioned is dated April 23, 1800: this appears to be an error in transcription from an original.
  Meade's role in the expedition to map Colombia's Atrato River is not clear from the correspondence: its mission was to map possible transisthmian sites before Panama was eventually chosen.
  The foldered log books of North Carolina appear to have been disbound from a volume similar to others in the collection. General orders have been pasted over the logbook entries in some places.
  The Spanish translations of various documents of American freedom, and correspondence documenting efforts to have them distributed to new Spanish-speaking citizens, are undated. They may date to soon after the annexation of Texas and other Spanish-speaking territories as a result of the Mexican-American War that ended in 1848.
  Much of the early correspondence bears the date, added in pencil, of the collection's acquisition by the Naval History Society: May 3, 1934. The subject of a few documents has been written on them in blue pencil.
  All the volumes show the bookplate of Richard Worsam Meade (a heraldic crest bearing the motto "Toujours prest") as well as a sticker with the Naval History Society's seal that reads "From the Library of Richard Worsam Meade 4th (1870-1833), son of Richard Worsam Meade (3rd), Rear Admiral U.S.N., presented by Mrs. Richard Worsam Meade (4th), May 3, 1934".
  In 1862, San Jacinto was under the command of Theodore Greene. His correspondence from 1863 to 1864 aboard that vessel forms part of Series 23 and was donated to the Naval History Society by Mrs. Meade as part of her 1934 gift.
  The loose materials had previously been arranged in chronological order by subject, with printed materials gathered together at the end. The thematic divisions have been retained but all foldered materials are now in chronological order.
  1807: Richard Worsam Meade 2nd born in Spain
  1826: Enters Navy as midshipman
  1826-1836: Serves aboard Brandywine, St. Louis
  1836: Marries Clara Forsyth Meigs
  1837: Son Richard Worsam Meade 3rd (see Series 31) born New York City
  1837: Promoted to lieutenant; serves with US Coast Survey, at New York Navy Yard, aboard steamer Fulton and storeship Erie
  1839: Lieutenant under Captain Gedney aboard brig Washington at capture of slave ship Amistad off Long Island coast, August
  1840s: Fulfils intermittent naval service while awaiting orders
  1847: Assigned to steamer Scourge
  1851: Resigns commission
  1854-1855: Resumes service as commanding officer aboard steamship Massachusetts in the Pacific Squadron
  1855: Resigns commission
  1861: Returns to active duty as Commander of receiving ship North Carolina at New York, on which new recruits are housed and trained before receiving their permanent assignments
  1864: Promoted to captain, commanding officer aboard San Jacinto during its pursuit and capture of various Confederate ships supplying southern ports
  1865: Supervises salvage of guns and equipment when San Jacinto strikes a reef off Great Abaco Island, Bahamas, January 1
  1867: Retires from active service
  1870: Dies Brooklyn, New York, April
  - Notes on navigation and mercator sailing, 1836-1837 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence about Amistad: watch bill, orders, officers aboard Washington, prize settlement, 1839 August - 1841 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Charles H. Smith, Perth Amboy, about Zabriskie, 1842 October 19 - December 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Log abstracts: Massachusetts, Decatur; log extract Dale; correspondence, 1842, 1851, 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence received; Vincennes log book; Charles Gray affidavit, 1843-1857 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence received, 1847-1867, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Edith: Inventory, inventory of public property, correspondence from chief engineer Parran to Commodore Thomas Catesby Jones, 1848-1849 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Congressional Record: Act to promote Navy efficiency; Bill to indemnify Amistad master and owners; report on Boutwell memorial, 1852, 1858, 1859, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Massachusetts: log, correspondence, 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Naval orders, circulars, publication on reorganization; form to document cruises, 1856, 1858, 1864, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Atrato River survey: correspondence to Isaac Toncey, and between Alexander von Humboldt and F.M. Kelly, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Muster roll of the band [North Carolina?], 1862 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - North Carolina: log book, extracts, general orders, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - List of deserters, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence sent and received, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Prisoners report, San Jacinto, 1862-1865 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - North Carolina: steam warming and ventilating apparatus, 18XX (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Extracts, log of San Jacinto, 1864 December (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Internal regulations, San Jacinto, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter book copies, correspondence San Jacinto, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Monthly quarterly returns as required by the Admiral," desertion reports, crew lists San Jacinto, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ordnance supplies, books aboard San Jacinto, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Prize list, San Jacinto, [1864] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reports, correspondence from San Jacinto, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Money expended on provisions, names of men blacklisted, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Stores, supplies from wreck of San Jacinto, 1865 January (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Statement of administrator of late Captain R.W. Meade, USN", 1871 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clipping: "Namesake of schooner slaves took over joining Operation Sail," New York Times, 1976 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ship plan, unidentified, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Translation from Spanish: "Nihilism", Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Explanation of translated documents' value, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence petitioning for compensation; Spanish translations of Declaration of Independence and other documents, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spanish translation, Articles of Confederation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Spanish translations, Declaration of Independence, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Spanish translation, U.S. Constitution, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Officers aboard Washington and prize money apportioned for capture of Amistad, [1840] April 23 (Box OS 1, Folder 15)
  - Copy, log book San Jacinto, 1864 January 31, 1865 January 2 (Box OS 1, Folder 16)
  - Crew list, San Jacinto, 1864 (Box OS 3, Folder 4)
  - Letter book, 1839 February 20 -1840 July 18 (Volume 1)
  - Pamphlets, letters, reprints about Lt. John T. McLaughlin, 1843-1845 (Volume 2)
  - List of Officers and Men, Pay Tables: USS San Jacinto, 1864 (Volume 3)
  - Watches, crews, and messes: USS San Jacinto, 1864 (Volume 4)
  - Letter book, 1864 January 3 - April 30 (Volume 5)
  - Internal regulations, list of deserters, USS San Jacinto; copies of 36 letters, 1864-1865 (Volume 6)
- Series 31. Richard Worsam Meade, 3rd (1853-1897, 1934)
  The collection is comprised of Admiral Meade's journals kept as a midshipman, including notes and sketches; teaching-related documents from his stint at the US Naval Academy; official correspondence received; letter books and orders from his service aboard various vessels (bound in 1939 by the Naval History Society); clippings and printed materials, including those documenting efforts to erect a commemorative statue to John Paul Jones in Washington, DC; drafts and final versions of his writings on John Paul Jones; other materials related to his administrative duties at the New York and Washington Navy Yards; eight volumes of diaries bound by the Naval History Society; and clippings and ephemera postdating his death that were probably collected by his wife.
  The correspondence includes that related to his 1870 negotiation of trading treaties with Tutuila-Samoa, and details of the 1883 outfitting of USS Pinta in preparation for its duty off Alaska. The 1891 copy of "Northwestern Architect" includes a description of the Navy Department's exhibition planned for the World Columbian Exposition in Chicago on page 63. The letterpress copies of 1894-1895 had been disbound from a letterpress book. The John Paul Jones material includes Admiral Meade's lecture presentation to the United Service Club in 1896 and information on his daughter Annie Paulding Meade's presentation on the subject in 1899. The scrapbook materials were found with miscellaneous papers of the Naval History Society and removed to this series.
  Many of the materials bear a sticker with the Naval History Society's seal that reads "From the Library of Richard Worsam Meade 4th (1870-1833), son of Richard Worsam Meade (3rd), Rear Admiral U.S.N., presented by Mrs. Richard Worsam Meade (4th), May 3, 1934". Subsequent contributions to the collection are documented through 1937.
  The Naval History Society's Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection (see Series 52) contains additional correspondence between Admiral Meade and John Sanford Barnes about John Paul Jones.
  The "Scrapbook of R.W. Meade, Rear Admiral", 1892-1898, was bound by the Naval History Society in 1939 and included in its library collection (XN E182.M52 oversize).
  1837: Born New York City October 8, son of Clara Meigs and Richard Worsam Meade 2nd (see Series 30)
  1853: Serves aboard St. Louis in Mediterranean
  1856: Graduates US Naval Academy
  1858: Commissioned lieutenant and assigned duty as ordnance instructor in receiving ship USS Ohio at Boston
  1862: Promoted to lieutenant commander 1862, in command of USS Louisville on Mississippi River
  1863: Commands a naval battalion during the July draft riots in New York City
  1865: Marries Rebecca Paulding (daughter of Admiral James Paulding, Secretary of the Navy 1838-1841)
  1865-1868: Head of Steamship Department, US Naval Academy
  1868: Commissioned commander; prepares Naval Academy's "Manual of the Boat Exercises"
  1870: Father Richard Worsam Meade 2nd dies; son Richard Worsam Meade 4th born
  1871-1873: Commands USS Narragansett on its cruise through the southwest Pacific islands to Australia; commended for skill in negotiating commercial treaty with Samoan Islands
  1883-1887: Commandant, New York Navy Yard
  1887-1890: Commandant, Washington Navy Yard